To finish this section on data protection,
let's look at some predefined security roles
within SQL Server. Roles have a big purpose, and
that is, to have pre-defined sets of permissions
that are applied to users, so that, in theory,
individual permissions do not need to be used
and thus tracked within both a server instance and
its databases, streamlining security with users.
As I expand the Security folder and then Server
Roles in this instance of SQL Server, understand
that for the exam the main focus in on the purpose
of roles, not having to know each individual role,
but having an idea of each role will help define
the overall purpose of roles. There are nine
pre-defined server roles and I am going to cover
these in the order of least restrictive to most
restrictive. First, we have sysadmin. One with
this role can perform any activity on the server,
so this role should be used sparingly. Next,
we have the serveradmin role, which allows
one to change server configurations and shut
down the server. The third role to look at is
securityadmin. A user in this role can grant and
revoke permissions on a server level and do the
same for databases on which they have permissions.
The fourth role to look at is processadmin, which
allows one to end running processes on a server,
such as a backup process that is taking far longer
than anticipated. Next we have the setupadmin
role, which allows one to add and remove linked
servers, which allow one to use queries to
get information from remote data sources,
such as another SQL server instance. The bulkadmin
role allows one to use a bulk insert statement,
which imports large amounts of data into a
database. The diskadmin role allows one to
manage disk files. The dbcreator role allows one
to create, alter, drop, and restore a database.
If you are wondering about a backup role,
you will see where it is and why soon.
Lastly, we have the public role, which is a
role that is assigned to everyone on a server,
so whatever permissions that are granted to
that role apply to everyone on a server. Thus,
one needs to be very careful about any
permissions assigned to the public role.